<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model https://raw.githubusercontent.com/i-d-e/ride/master/schema/ride.rng application/xml http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0?>
<?xml-model https://raw.githubusercontent.com/i-d-e/ride/master/schema/ride.rng application/xml http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ride.9.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>EDITORIAL: Digital Text Collections, the third</title>
            <author ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2852-065X">
               <name>
                  <forename>Ulrike</forename>
                  <surname>Henny-Krahmer</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>University of Würzburg</orgName>
                   <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/2805615">Würzburg, Germany</placeName>
               </affiliation>
               <email>ulrike.henny@uni-wuerzburg.de</email>
            </author>
            <author ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298">
               <name>
                  <forename>Frederike</forename>
                  <surname>Neuber</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
                   <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/2950159">Berlin, Germany</placeName>
               </affiliation>
               <email>neuber@bbaw.de</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Institut für Dokumentologie und Editorik e. V.</publisher>
            <date when="2018-11">November 2018</date>
            <idno type="URI">http://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-9/editorial</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">10.18716/ride.a.9.0</idno>
            <idno type="archive">https://github.com/i-d-e/ride/raw/master/issues/issue09/editorial/editorial.pdf</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">RIDE - A review journal for digital editions and resources</title>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2852-065X">Ulrike Henny-Krahmer</editor>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298">Frederike Neuber</editor>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6457-0913" role="managing">Philipp
                    Steinkrüger</editor>
            <editor ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/80243768" role="technical">Bernhard
                    Assmann</editor>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2852-065X" role="technical">Ulrike
                    Henny-Krahmer</editor>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298" role="technical">Frederike
                    Neuber</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="9">Digital Text Collections</biblScope>
            <idno type="URI">http://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-9</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">10.18716/ride.a.9</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>editorial</term>
               <term>text collection</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="div1">
            <p xml:id="p1">We are happy to present the third volume on the topic of Digital Text
                    Collections (DTC) which is also the ninth volume in the entire RIDE series. With
                    this issue, we publish the last reviews that we received as a reaction to the
                    first <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/reviewers/call-for-reviews/special-issue-text-collections/">call for reviews on DTCs</ref>, together with several additional
                    contributions. The current issue also represents a milestone for RIDE as a
                    whole: With the five reviews of the current issue, a total of 50 reviews are now
                    available in RIDE, including 20 on DTC and 30 on Digital Scholarly Editions.</p>
            <p xml:id="p2">As in the previous volumes, the rationale of the reviews is based on
                    the <ref target="https://www.i-d-e.de/publikationen/weitereschriften/criteria-text-collections-version-1-0/">guidelines for evaluating text collections</ref>. In addition, each article
                    is accompanied by a factsheet that summarises the most important information on
                    the resource evaluated. A selection of this data, gathered with a <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/data/questionnaire-text-collections/">questionnaire</ref> and summarized for all the factsheets on DTCs so far,
                    is visualized <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/data/charts-text-collections/">here</ref> as a set of charts.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div2">
            <head>Contents</head>
            <p xml:id="p3">The current volume contains five reviews, two in English and three in
                    German. Three of the reviews in this volume are dedicated to linguistic corpora,
                    including Czech, Spanish, and multilingual resources. One review addresses a
                    collection of literary texts in English. The fifth review is devoted to a
                    collection of texts from a completely different context: Ancient Papyrology. The
                    reviewed resources are all DTCs that already look back on a longer history of
                    existence and development. The most recent of the resources reviewed in this
                    issue is <emph>Papyri.info</emph> which was still already launched in 2010 and
                    has been reviewed by Lucia Vannini.<note xml:id="ftn1">Vannini, Lucia. "Review
                        of papyri.info." RIDE 9 (2018). doi: 10.18716/ride.a.9.4. <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/papyri-info/">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/papyri-info/</ref>, accessed: November 2,
                        2018.</note>
               <emph>InterCorp</emph>, reviewed by Agnes Kim<note xml:id="ftn2">Kim, Agnes.
                        "Review of 'InterCorp – Ein mehrsprachiges Parallelkorpus des Tschechischen
                        Nationalkorpus (Český národní korpus)'." RIDE 9 (2018). doi:
                        10.18716/ride.a.9.1. <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/intercorp/">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/intercorp/</ref>, accessed: November 2,
                        2018.</note>, <emph>ShakespearePlaysPlus</emph>, reviewed by Katharina
                        Mahler<note xml:id="ftn3">Mahler, Katharina. "Review of
                        “ShakespearePlaysPlus Text Corpus”." RIDE 9 (2018). doi:
                        10.18716/ride.a.9.3. <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/shakespeare-plays/">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/shakespeare-plays/</ref>, accessed:
                        November 2, 2018.</note>, and the <emph>European Parliament Proceedings
                        Parallel Corpus (Europarl)</emph>, reviewed by Claes Neuefeind<note xml:id="ftn4">Neuefeind, Claes. "Rezension von Europarl." RIDE 9 (2018).
                        doi: 10.18716/ride.a.9.2. <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/europarl/">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/europarl/</ref>, accessed: November 2,
                        2018.</note>, have already surpassed the first decade of their existence and
                    were published in 2005, 2006, and 2001, respectively. <emph>CORLEC</emph>, a
                    corpus of oral conversations in contemporary Spanish which has been reviewed by
                    Katrin Betz<note xml:id="ftn5">Betz, Katrin. "Rezension des „Corpus Oral de
                        Referencia de la Lengua Española Contempóranea“." RIDE 9 (2018). doi:
                        10.18716/ride.a.9.5. <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/corlec/">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/corlec/</ref>, accessed: November 2,
                        2018.</note>, has even existed for almost two decades (since 1991).</p>
            <p xml:id="p4">
               <figure xml:id="img1">
                  <graphic url="http://ride.i-d-e.de/wp-content/uploads/issue_9/editorial/pictures/picture-1.png"/>
                  <head type="legend">Research fields (top left), eras (top right), languages
                            (bottom left), and types of text (bottom right) for DTCs.</head>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="img2">
                  <graphic url="http://ride.i-d-e.de/wp-content/uploads/issue_9/editorial/pictures/picture-2.png"/>
                  <head type="legend">Word clouds of the five reviews in RIDE issue 9.</head>
               </figure> Looking at the diversity of content of all the DTCs reviewed in RIDE
                    so far, most reviews addressed resources from the fields of Literature and
                    Linguistics, followed by resources contributing to research in History. There
                    are more reviews on texts belonging to the early modern, modern, and
                    contemporary era than to the medieval or classical era. Regarding languages,
                    English and German texts are most common, but especially the multilingual
                    resources led to a broad language spectrum of the DTCs reviewed in RIDE so far.
                    As for the types of text, DTCs containing literary works have been evaluated
                    most often, followed by collections which include newspaper and journal articles
                    (see <ref type="crossref" target="#img1">Fig. 1</ref>). When compared to the
                    general trends, the composition of the current issue reflects them quite well,
                    with a special focus on linguistic corpora. Despite the different contents and
                    languages of the resources examined, it is possible to have a comparative glance
                    at the DTCs of the current issue in terms of their history, methods and
                    practices.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div3">
            <head>Temporality</head>
            <p xml:id="p5">A recurring challenge in the evaluation of digital resources, which
                    we have also discussed in the <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-8/editorial/">editorial of the
                        previous issue on DTCs</ref>, is to take into account the temporality of a
                    digital resource on several levels when it is reviewed, used, and evaluated. If
                    older resources are no longer actively developed and updated, they reflect a
                    particular historical methodological state of the art which may not bear
                    comparison with similar resources which were created later on. Nonetheless, they
                    are still valuable, especially if they grew out of major projects with a
                    comprehensive goal and if they constitute fundamental research which has not
                    been repeated since then.</p>
            <p xml:id="p6">Regarding <emph>CORLEC</emph>, conceived as a reference corpus for
                    contemporary spoken Spanish, Betz states that it is still an important resource
                    for researchers interested in the field, despite its somewhat outdated
                        methods:<note xml:id="ftn6">Daniel Kozák evaluated <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-8/phi/">
                     <emph>PHI Latin Texts</emph> in the previous issue of RIDE</ref> in a
                        similar way by saying that even if the methods used by <emph>PHI</emph> do
                        not meet today’s standard, the DTC is widely used in practice and therefore
                        deserves a positive overall evaluation.</note> “It must be anticipated here
                    that certain features and characteristics of <emph>CORLEC</emph>, which are
                    perceived as deficiencies today, met the standards or were even innovative at
                    the moment of its creation. Therefore, its comparability with modern corpora in
                    terms of composition and size are limited”.<note xml:id="ftn7">“Deshalb soll
                        hier vorweggenommen werden, dass bestimmte Merkmale und Eigenschaften des
                            <emph>CORLEC</emph>, die heute als Mangel wahrgenommen werden, zu der
                        Zeit seiner Erstellung wohl dem Standard entsprachen oder aber innovativ
                        waren. Das Korpus ist daher in seiner Zusammensetzung und Größe nur bedingt
                        mit modernen Korpora [...] vergleichbar” (translated into English by the
                        editors). Betz 2018, § 4, <ref type="crossref" target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/corlec/#p4">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/corlec/#p4</ref>.</note> Betz decides not
                    to subject <emph>CORLEC</emph> to an evaluative comparison with similar modern
                    corpora, but to concentrate on its own characteristics. <emph>Europarl</emph>,
                    in contrast, has been updated several times since it was first published in 2001
                    - its latest version dating from 2012, also due to successive funding periods.
                    Neuefeind explains that the corpus has grown steadily with regards to the number
                    of languages and words. In the case of <emph>Europarl</emph>, all the different
                    versions are still accessible. Like <emph>CORLEC</emph>, also
                        <emph>Europarl</emph> is still in use: “Although this is an older corpus, it
                    was prepared in a way that still meets the usual standards for the creation of
                    parallel corpora für machine translation. The <emph>Europarl</emph> corpus is
                    therefore still often used, for example as a baseline or benchmark in the
                    development and evaluation of classical systems of statistical machine
                    translation (SMT) [...]”.<note xml:id="ftn8">“Wenngleich es sich um ein älteres
                        Korpus handelt, so entspricht diese Art der Aufbereitung nach wie vor den
                        üblichen Standards zur Erstellung von Parallelkorpora für die maschinelle
                        Übersetzung. Das <emph>Europarl</emph>-Korpus wird dementsprechend noch
                        immer häufig eingesetzt, etwa als <emph>baseline</emph> bzw.
                            <emph>benchmark</emph> in der Entwicklung und Evaluation klassischer
                        SMT-Systeme [...]” (translated into English by the editors). Neuefeind 2018,
                        § 13, <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/europarl/#p13">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/europarl/#p13</ref>.</note> The ongoing
                    interest in the <emph>Europarl</emph> corpus is evidenced by the fact that it is
                    also included into other aggregated corpora, for example <emph>InterCorp</emph>,
                    reviewed in this same issue of RIDE, where it is part of the so-called
                    “collections”: texts integrated into the core corpus from external resources.
                    Such integration of external sources, or more specifically the aggregation of
                    various independent resources is in itself a point worth of discussion, because
                    it poses special challenges for the editors and administrators of a resource,
                    for its users and also for reviewers.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div4">
            <head>Aggregated resources</head>
            <p xml:id="p7">When DTCs consist completely or partly of external resources, several
                    questions arise such as: When were different parts integrated into the
                    collection and how does this affect its integrity? How stable are the sources of
                    a collection over time? The last two questions are especially relevant in the
                    case of the Czech parallel corpus <emph>InterCorp</emph> and papyrological
                    portal <emph>Papyri.info</emph> which rely partly or entirely on aggregated
                    texts from external resources.</p>
            <p xml:id="p8">
               <emph>InterCorp</emph> is partly based on aggregated resources, in that it
                    consists of a core corpus which has been manually aligned, and an extended
                    collection of aggregated pre-existing resources which have been automatically
                    aligned. In qualitative terms, the aggregated texts differ from the corpus
                    because of their automatic alignment. As such, according to Kim, they have many
                    more incorrect alignments.<note xml:id="ftn9">Cf. Kim 2018, § 10, <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/intercorp/#p10">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/intercorp/#p10</ref>.</note> In addition,
                    the metadata of the aggregated resources is often missing or incomplete.
                        <emph>Papyri.info</emph> deals with similar challenges. It is a platform in
                    which resources from several different origins are aggregated and at the same
                    time it offers a research environment for collaborative work on the joined
                    materials. Because of this, updates of the sources challenge the synchronisation
                    of the integrated resources and sometimes the transparency of the data’s origin
                    is jeopardized.<note xml:id="ftn10">In her review, Vannini describes how the
                        update process on <emph>Papyri.info</emph> is organized for those source
                        collections that still exist independently. On the other hand, one of the
                        source collections ceded to exist on its own when it was integrated into the
                        portal and yet another one still exists but its changes are not reflected in
                            <emph>Papyri.info</emph>. Cf. Vannini, § 11f., <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/papyri-info/#p11">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/papyri-info/#p11</ref>. </note>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="p9">The described challenges are a strong case for the relevance of a
                    review. In the case of <emph>InterCorp</emph>, the reviewer learned about the
                    problems and peculiarities of aggregated resources through the resource’s own
                    documentation. For <emph>Papyri.info</emph> much of the information regarding
                    the state of the data and the update procedures was obtained by the reviewer
                    only through personal communication with those responsible for the resource. For
                    better transparency and reproducibility, however, it would be helpful for users
                    if this was documented on the website. Generally, aggregated resources can be a
                    complex set-up and the reviews can help to disentangle the dependencies for a
                    novice user.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div5">
            <head>Text and Tools</head>
            <p xml:id="p10">Some of the DTCs in this issue are strongly connected and/or
                    dependent on the use of certain research tools.
                        <emph>ShakespearePlaysPlus</emph>, for example, has been designed explicitly
                    for the WordSmith Tools which is reflected in its data model, its primary usage
                    possibilities, and also its place of publication on the WordSmith Tools
                        website.<note xml:id="ftn11">Cf. Mahler 2018, <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/shakespeare-plays/">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/shakespeare-plays/</ref>.</note>
               <emph>InterCorp</emph> is accessible via the corpus manager KonText,<note xml:id="ftn12">Cf. Kim 2018, § 32ff., <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/intercorp/#p32">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/intercorp/#p32</ref>.</note> “an advanced
                    corpus query interface and corpus data integration middleware built around
                    corpus search engine Manatee-open”<note xml:id="ftn13">
                  <ref target="https://web.archive.org/web/20181102152657/https://github.com/czcorpus/kontext">https://web.archive.org/web/20181102152657/https://github.com/czcorpus/kontext</ref>.
                    </note>, developed by the Institute of the Czech National Corpus and used for
                    several different corpora. Europarl is not dependent on third-party tools, but
                    published together with a set of scripts for sentence splitting and alignment
                    which enable the user to create a corpus of the desired language pairs on the
                    fly. It can thus rather be considered a toolkit for a parallel corpus than a
                    finished product.<note xml:id="ftn14">Cf. Neuefeind 2018, § 8, <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/europarl/#p8">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/europarl/#p8</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="p11">There will rarely be any DTC which does not rely on any tool for its
                    development or use. So far, in our <ref target="https://www.i-d-e.de/publikationen/weitereschriften/criteria-text-collections-version-1-0">criteria for reviewing DTCs</ref> the role of tools is addressed at several
                    points. For instance, it is asked whether tools are provided to analyse the DTC
                    further and if the data can be examined with other tools easily. However, all
                    these questions always refer strongly to the textual data, less to the tool as
                    an independent research object, which in turn would have to be subject to it's
                    very own criteria of reviewing.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div6">
            <head>Rethinking Classification?</head>
            <p xml:id="p12">In the earlier editorials,<note xml:id="ftn15">See <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-6/editorial-reviewing-digital-text-collections/">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-6/editorial-reviewing-digital-text-collections/</ref>
                        and <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-8/editorial/">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-8/editorial/</ref>.</note> we spent
                    some thoughts on how DTCs could be classified further. Our first approach of a
                    classification scheme was based on a terminology relying primarily on the kinds
                    of materials that are collected in a resource (collection of literary texts,
                    letters, historical documents, inscriptions etc.) and the research aims of a
                    collection (e.g. establishment of a canon, comparison, evolution over
                        time).<note xml:id="ftn16">Currently, the typology includes: General purpose
                        collection, Corpus, Collection of records, Canon, Complete works/œuvre,
                        Reference corpus, Contrastive corpus, Parallel corpus, and Diachronic
                        corpus. Cf. <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-6/editorial-reviewing-digital-text-collections/">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-6/editorial-reviewing-digital-text-collections/</ref>.</note>
                    Terminologies used by creators of DTCs and by scholars discussing them pointed
                    out other important factors for a classification such as aspects of preserving,
                    technical and presentational organization (archive, library, database, portal).
                    Still, the reviews on DTCs so far have revealed that our current scheme of
                    classification may not be enough to capture significant nuances of different
                    types of DTCs.</p>
            <p xml:id="p13">With the current issue, for example, it became clear to us that
                    resources can differ significantly in aspects with minor importance in
                    traditional taxonomies of DTCs, even if they usually are considered to be of the
                    same type. For instance, <emph>InterCorp</emph> and <emph>Europarl</emph> are
                    both parallel corpora by definition, but the resources differ in a significant
                    point: their research paradigm and their “target group”. <emph>InterCorp</emph>
                    was created in the first place as a human-readable corpus. Kim stresses in her
                    review that “<emph>InterCorp</emph> [...] explicitly addresses human users and
                    tries to meet their needs.”<note xml:id="ftn17">“Das <emph>InterCorp</emph>
                        richtet sich [...] explizit an menschliche NutzerInnen und versucht deren
                        Bedürfnissen nachzukommen” (translated into English by the editors). Kim
                        2018, § 2, <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/intercorp/#p2">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/intercorp/#p2</ref>.</note>
               <emph>Europarl</emph>, on the other hand has “no dedicated user interface, since
                        <emph>Europarl</emph> is primarily meant to support research on machine
                    translation, which has to rely on parallel texts”, as Neuefeind explains.<note xml:id="ftn18">Neuefeind 2018, abstract, <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/europarl/#abstract">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/europarl/#abstract</ref>.</note> From a
                    user’s and reviewer’s point of view, the quality of these two DTCs is strikingly
                    different which shows that kinds of interfaces, accessibility and usage
                    scenarios are aspects which also should be taken into account in a typology of
                    DTCs.</p>
            <p xml:id="p14">One possibility would be to identify and define DTCs on more levels
                    but this would certainly lead to a typology which is farther away from known
                    categories. Already now, reviewers tend to assign the resources to a range of
                    types which shows that the resources are either not easily classifiable, that
                    the categories are not very well-established, or that they may not be easily
                    integrated into a typological system. In the current issue, for instance,
                    Vannini identifies <emph>Papyri.info</emph> as “General purpose collection”,
                    “Corpus”, and “Reference corpus”<note xml:id="ftn19">Cf. <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/papyri-info/factsheet/">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/papyri-info/factsheet/</ref>.</note>
                    while Mahler identifies <emph>ShakespearePlaysPlus</emph> as “Corpus”, “Canon”,
                    and “Complete works”.<note xml:id="ftn20">Cf. <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/shakespeare-plays/factsheet/">https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-9/shakespeare-plays/factsheet/</ref>.</note>
                    Another approach would be to rethink the architecture of the classification
                    scheme as a whole. So far we built the typology “top-down” by defining types of
                    DTCs and assigning them characteristics. Thinking “bottom-up”, types of DTCs
                    would be build only by the combination of characteristics. Such an approach
                    where characteristics are not bound to certain classes would probably be more
                    suitable in the long term to sufficiently capture all the nuances of DTCs which
                    emerge in the still growing and fast changing field of digital (text)
                    technologies. It could also make it easier for the reviewers to decide what
                    characteristics a resource has instead of assigning it to a predefined concept.
                    It can be assumed that such a bottom-up system based on many different
                    characteristics will lead to a “fine threaded carpet” of text collections with
                    relations and similarities on many different levels. Therefore, it seems
                    reasonable to combine both strategies and not to give up the idea of a typology
                    integrating existing categories entirely. Certainly, in the future we will
                    consider both options and evaluate modifications of our taxonomy.</p>
            <p xml:id="p15">To sum up, as editors we found that all the reviews together provide
                    an excellent empirical basis for digging into the ground of digital scholarship
                    which we hope will grow and be explored by the readers of RIDE. Not to forget
                    the valuable discussion of an individual DTC by each review as well as its
                    contribution to the critical discourse on digital scholarly resources, which it
                    helps to keep alive and to mature.</p>
            <p xml:id="p16">We thank the authors of this issue and the peer reviewers involved
                    in the creation of this issue for their enthusiasm, commitment, and also
                    patience. Special thanks to Bernhard Assmann for the “typesetting” and to all of
                    the IDE.</p>
            <p>Enjoy the ride!</p>
            <p>The editors, Ulrike Henny-Krahmer and Frederike Neuber, November 2018.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
