<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model https://raw.githubusercontent.com/i-d-e/ride/master/schema/ride.rng application/xml http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0?>
<?xml-model https://raw.githubusercontent.com/i-d-e/ride/master/schema/ride.rng application/xml http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ride.21.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Crowd Editions: Participation, Expertise and Automation in Digital Scholarly Editing</title>
            <author ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5584-4807">
               <name>
                  <forename>Anna</forename>
                  <surname>Busch</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>Universität Potsdam</orgName>
                  <placeName>Potsdam</placeName>
               </affiliation>
               <email>anna.busch@uni-potsdam.de</email>
            </author>
            <author ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3152-6542">
               <name>
                  <forename>Martin</forename>
                  <surname>Prell</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>Sächsische Akademie der Wissenschaften zu Leipzig</orgName>
                  <placeName>Weimar</placeName>
               </affiliation>
               <email>martin.prell@klassik-stiftung.de</email>
            </author>
            <author ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3152-6542">
               <name>
                  <forename>Torsten</forename>
                  <surname>Roeder</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>Julius-Maximilians-Universität Würzburg</orgName>
                  <placeName>Würzburg</placeName>
               </affiliation>
               <email>torsten.roeder@uni-wuerzburg.de</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Institut für Dokumentologie und Editorik e.V.</publisher>
            <date when="2026-05">May 2026</date>
            <idno type="URI">http://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-21/editorial</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">10.18716/ride.a.21.0</idno>
            <idno type="archive">https://github.com/i-d-e/ride/raw/master/issues/issue21/editorial/editorial.pdf</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">RIDE - A review journal for digital editions and resources</title>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5584-4807">Anna Busch</editor>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3152-6542">Martin Prell</editor>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7043-7820">Torsten Roeder</editor>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2852-065X" role="managing">Ulrike Henny-Krahmer</editor>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236" role="managing">Martina Scholger</editor>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0004-5854-8869" role="technical">Magdalena Victoria Basedow</editor>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0009-0005-6203-2942" role="technical">Finnja Borchardt</editor>
            <editor ref="none" role="technical">Julia Dobesberger</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="21">Digital Scholarly Editions (Crowdsourcing)</biblScope>
            <idno type="URI">http://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-21</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="div1">
             <head>Crowd Editions: Participation, Expertise and Automation in Digital Scholarly Editing</head>
            <p xml:id="p1">The idea that scholarly knowledge is generated by the many rather than the few
                    gained renewed momentum in the early 2000s. As an alternative to small,
                    selective expert editorial teams, projects such as Wikipedia and Wikisource have
                    demonstrated that large, loosely organised digital communities can catalogue,
                    structure and make extensive bodies of knowledge publicly accessible. Such forms
                    of collective knowledge production have since been widely discussed under the
                    term <emph>crowdsourcing</emph> and have given rise to new ways of
                    working, particularly in the fields of cultural heritage research and the
                    digital humanities (<ref type="crossref" target="#terras2015">Terras 2015</ref>; <ref type="crossref" target="#ridge_2017">Ridge 2017</ref>). In the field of digital editions,
                    too, projects have emerged since the 2010s that open up tasks within the
                    editorial process to a wider public.</p>
            <p xml:id="p2">However, with the increasing digitisation of humanities work processes, it is not
                    only the technical tools of editorial practice that have changed, but also the
                    institutional and social context of scholarly practice. Keywords such as <emph>Open Science</emph>, <emph>Citizen Science</emph>, <emph>Public Humanities</emph> or <emph>Participation</emph>
                    signal a shift towards viewing research as a social process and towards
                    exploring new forms of collaboration between academic institutions and the
                    public. In the field of digital editions in particular, collaborative working
                    methods have developed in this context, discussed under terms such as <emph>crowdsourcing</emph>, <emph>social editing</emph> or
                        <emph>crowd editing</emph>.</p>
            <p xml:id="p3">Currently, the question also arises as to what extent crowdsourcing, as a method
                    of digital knowledge aggregation, is falling behind due to competition from
                    generative artificial intelligence processes (<ref type="crossref" target="#christoforou_etal2025">Christoforou, Demartini, and Otterbacher 2025</ref>)
                    – or what advantages it continues to offer as an effective method of data
                    extraction. Advances in automated processes in areas such as OCR, handwriting
                    recognition or text-based analysis have triggered a new debate on the
                    relationship between algorithmic and human forms of knowledge production. Crowd
                    editions thus also illustrate the general transformation of editorial practice,
                    in which questions of expertise, participation and automation are being
                    renegotiated.</p>
            <p xml:id="p4">This special issue of the review journal RIDE is dedicated to these developments
                    under the heading of <emph>Crowd Editions</emph>. The aim is to review
                    digital editorial projects that employ participatory working methods and make
                    parts of the editorial process accessible to a wider public. The reviews
                    collected in this volume examine such projects from various perspectives and
                    explore the extent to which participatory methods are compatible with the
                    scholarly requirements of digital editions.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div2">
            <head>Concepts and Models of Participatory Editing</head>
            <p xml:id="p5">The discussion of participatory forms of editing is closely linked to a range
                        of terms whose usage in scholarly discourse is not always unambiguous. A
                        distinction is often made between <emph>social editions</emph> and
                            <emph>crowdsourced editions</emph>. Whilst social editions
                        usually refer to collaborative projects in which a community makes editorial
                        decisions and edits texts collectively (<ref type="crossref" target="#crompton_etal2013">Crompton, Arbuckle, and Siemens 2013</ref>), crowdsourcing generally
                        refers to a form of division of labour in which clearly defined tasks are
                        delegated to a larger group of participants (<ref type="crossref" target="#martin_etal2008">Martin, Lessmann, and Voß 2008</ref>).</p>
            <p xml:id="p6">In practice, these models often overlap. Many projects combine different
                        forms of participation and cannot easily be assigned to a single category.
                        The term <emph>citizen science</emph> is also increasingly used in
                        the context of humanities research, although its applicability to the
                        humanities is not without controversy (<ref type="crossref" target="#smolarski_etal2023">Smolarski, Carius, and Prell 2023</ref>).</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div3">
            <head>Historical Development</head>
            <p xml:id="p7">The involvement of a wider public in academic projects is not a fundamentally
                        new phenomenon. In the natural sciences, forms of voluntary data collection
                        or observation have long existed, which are now summarised under the term
                            <emph>citizen science</emph>. In the digital humanities, the
                        concept of <emph>crowdsourcing</emph> in particular has played a
                        central role. Melissa Terras describes crowdsourcing in the digital
                        humanities as a method whereby tasks traditionally carried out by a small
                        circle of experts are outsourced to a larger group of voluntary or
                        semi-professional contributors (<ref type="crossref" target="#terras2015">Terras 2015</ref>).</p>
            <p xml:id="p8">The use of crowdsourcing in the digital humanities began to emerge in the
                        early 2000s, in parallel with the development of collaborative platforms
                        such as Wikipedia. An example is the <emph>Distributed
                            Proofreaders</emph> project (Charles Franks, 2000), in which digitised
                        texts are proofread by volunteers before being uploaded to <emph>Project Gutenberg</emph> (Michael S. Hart, 1971). The work is broken down
                        into small units – usually individual pages – and processed in parallel by
                        many contributors. A key motivation for participants is to be an active part
                        of the crowd and the growing collaborative effort.</p>
            <p xml:id="p9">The <emph>Transcribe Bentham</emph> project, launched in 2010,
                        represented a decisive step towards scholarly editorial work. The project
                        invited volunteers to transcribe manuscript pages from the extensive papers
                        of the philosopher <emph>Jeremy Bentham</emph> and to carry out
                        basic TEI encoding. This marked the first time that a demanding editorial
                        task had been systematically opened up to a wider public.</p>
            <p xml:id="p10">The success of this project has significantly influenced the discussion on
                        participatory forms of editing. Tens of thousands of manuscript pages were
                        transcribed and encoded, and the resulting data is being incorporated into
                        the preparation of the printed complete works of Bentham. At the same time,
                        the project has demonstrated that crowdsourcing can be not only a method for
                        generating large volumes of data, but also a way of involving interested
                        laypeople in scholarly processes (<ref type="crossref" target="#busch_roeder2023">Busch and
                            Roeder 2023</ref>).</p>
            <p xml:id="p11">In this context, Ben Brumfield coined the term <emph>accidental
                            editors</emph> to describe those voluntary contributors who, through their
                        participation in transcription projects, acquire editorial skills and thus
                        effectively become contributors to scholarly editorial projects (<ref type="crossref" target="#brumfield2017">Brumfield 2017</ref>). This observation suggests
                        that the boundary between professional and voluntary editorial work in
                        participatory projects is becoming increasingly blurred.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div4">
            <head>Crowdsourcing in the Digital Humanities and in Digital Editorial
                        Projects</head>
            <p xml:id="p12">In the field of digitised cultural heritage and scholarly digital editions,
                        such approaches have been established since the 2000s. Mia Ridge has
                        demonstrated in several studies that crowdsourcing projects in libraries,
                        archives and museums often serve not only to generate data, but also play an
                        important role in scholarly communication and social participation (<ref type="crossref" target="#ridge_2017">Ridge 2017</ref>; <ref type="crossref" target="#ridge_etal2021">Ridge, Blickhan, and Ferriter 2021</ref>). Examples in this volume
                        include the <emph>Crowdsourcing Wien</emph> project (reviewed by
                            <ref target="https://doi.org/10.18716/ride.a.21.5">Christian
                            Erlinger</ref>) and <emph>What’s On the Menu</emph> (reviewed
                        by <ref target="https://doi.org/10.18716/ride.a.21.3">Janosch
                        Förster</ref>). Participatory projects can thus both generate research data
                        and establish new forms of interaction between academic institutions and the
                        public. This is evident not only in historical everyday documents such as
                        postcards and menus, but particularly in material where collective,
                        intangible knowledge is the central focus of scholarly investigation, as in
                            <emph>Making and Knowing</emph> (reviewed by <ref target="https://doi.org/10.18716/ride.a.21.4">Sarah Lang</ref>).</p>
            <p xml:id="p13">In the field of scholarly editing, this approach may initially seem unusual.
                        Editions are traditionally regarded as highly specialised scholarly
                        products, the creation of which requires extensive specialist knowledge.
                        Accordingly, opening up this process to a wider public was initially viewed
                        with scepticism. In some cases, however – particularly in smaller and
                        geographically dispersed specialist communities – the ‘crowd’ is also
                        understood as a potentially globally distributed collective of experts. An
                        example of this in this volume is the <emph>Papyrological
                            Editor</emph> (reviewed by <ref target="https://doi.org/10.18716/ride.a.21.2">Lavinia Ferretti and Elisa
                            Nury</ref>), whilst <emph>#everynamecounts</emph> (reviewed by
                            <ref target="https://doi.org/10.18716/ride.a.21.1">Daniel
                            Burckhardt</ref>) demonstrates that initial expert platforms can indeed
                        transform into citizen science portals.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div5">
            <head>Opportunities and Challenges</head>
            <p xml:id="p14">Integrating a crowd into editorial workflows promises several advantages. One
                        of the most important aspects is the ability to process large volumes of
                        source material that small research teams could scarcely manage on their
                        own. Particularly in projects involving large manuscript collections or vast
                        amounts of source material, the participation of many individuals can
                        significantly accelerate data collection. However, ethical concerns are
                        sometimes raised when crowdsourcing is viewed merely as a means of obtaining
                        cheap labour and the public engagement aspect is disregarded (<ref type="crossref" target="#busch_etal2025">Busch, Roeder, and Prell 2025</ref>).</p>
            <p xml:id="p15">Furthermore, participatory projects can play an important role in scholarly
                        communication and social participation. The involvement of interested
                        citizens can help to raise the profile of humanities research and establish
                        new forms of interaction between research institutions and the public.
                        However, this process is by no means one-sided: in addition to recognition
                        for their contribution, citizen scientists also gain in-depth knowledge of
                        the material, thereby creating forms of knowledge distribution that in some
                        respects anticipate traditional forms of scientific public engagement.</p>
            <p xml:id="p16">At the same time, crowdsourcing projects involve considerable organisational
                        challenges. As several studies have shown, the successful use of
                        participatory methods requires careful project management as well as
                        continuous support for the participating community (<ref type="crossref" target="#ridge_2017">Ridge 2017</ref>). Crowdsourcing is therefore not a
                        simple tool for reducing workload; on the contrary, it often requires
                        additional resources for community management, technical infrastructure and
                        quality assurance. Worth mentioning in this volume on this topic is the
                        review of <emph>What’s on the Menu</emph>, not least because the
                        service has since been discontinued by its operators, and the review thus
                        also serves a documentary function.</p>
            <p xml:id="p17">Issues of academic quality also play a central role. Contributions from a
                        large and heterogeneous group of participants must be reviewed and
                        integrated consistently. In many projects, multi-stage control mechanisms
                        are used for this purpose, such as editorial checks, peer validation within
                        the crowd, or automated verification procedures. However, it is also the
                        case that a crowd community evolves over time into an <emph>expert crowd</emph>, which in turn can contribute to increasing
                        self-regulation and quality assurance within the community, provided that
                        adequate opportunities for exchange exist.</p>
            <p xml:id="p18">The discussion on crowdsourcing is also influenced today by advances in the
                        field of artificial intelligence. Automatic handwriting recognition, OCR
                        processes and large language models open up new possibilities for processing
                        historical texts. In the Digital Humanities, such processes now take on
                        tasks that were previously considered typical applications of crowdsourcing,
                        such as the transcription and annotation of historical documents. At the
                        same time, the question arises as to whether human crowd work, or parts
                        thereof, could be replaced by automated processes in the long term.</p>
            <p xml:id="p19">Within the Digital Humanities, however, this development is increasingly
                        understood not as a simple substitution of human labour by machines, but as
                        a transformation of the work processes themselves. Although automated
                        methods enable the faster processing of large volumes of text, they remain
                        dependent on training data, which often originates from previously manually
                        generated or curated datasets. Crowdsourcing projects have contributed
                        significantly to the creation of such <emph>ground truth</emph>
                        corpora, which serve as training and evaluation data for handwriting
                        recognition, OCR or other forms of automated text analysis. The crowd thus
                        functions not only as a workforce in the editorial process, but also as a
                        producer of key data infrastructures upon which many AI applications in the
                        digital humanities are built.</p>
            <p xml:id="p20">Current research, therefore, suggests that the relationship between human and
                        machine work is more complex than a simple competitive perspective would
                        suggest. Whilst automated methods now achieve remarkable results in many
                        areas, well-trained citizen scientists can still achieve a very high level
                        of accuracy in certain tasks (<ref type="crossref" target="#brumfield_evans2025">Brumfield
                            and Evans 2024</ref>). This applies in particular to material that
                        exhibits a high degree of diversity (e.g. typescripts and manuscripts) and
                        consists of small or abstract documents (e.g. index cards). Automated
                        methods continue to reach their limits, particularly with highly variable
                        layouts, damaged documents or idiosyncratic handwriting (<ref type="crossref" target="#werner_cugliana2026">Werner and Cugliana 2026</ref>), whereas
                        human editors can contribute contextual knowledge and interpretative
                        skills.</p>
            <p xml:id="p21">Furthermore, crowdsourcing and AI methods differ not only in terms of their
                        technical capabilities but also in terms of their scientific functions. In
                        the current DH debate, it is repeatedly pointed out that algorithmic methods
                        often operate as ‘black boxes’, whose decision-making processes are only
                        partially comprehensible to users. Participatory projects, on the other
                        hand, can make editorial decisions visible and enable scholarly work
                        processes to be designed transparently. In this sense, crowd editions
                        contribute not only to data generation but also to the epistemic
                        traceability of editorial work.</p>
            <p xml:id="p22">At the same time, crowdsourcing projects often fulfil additional roles within
                        the research landscape. They serve, for instance, as instruments of
                        scholarly communication, education or social participation, and make it
                        possible to make historical source collections accessible to a wider public.
                        This aspect can only be replaced to a limited extent by automated
                        processes.</p>
            <p xml:id="p23">This suggests that future working models may rely more heavily on <emph>hybrid approaches</emph>, combining automated processes with
                        human collaboration. In such models, AI systems can, for example, handle
                        initial transcription or recognition steps, whilst the crowd is deployed for
                        corrections, contextualisation or more complex interpretative tasks. The
                        role of the crowd thus potentially shifts from primary data collection
                        towards tasks of validation, curation and interpretation of algorithmically
                        generated results.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="div6">
            <head>Conclusion and Outlook</head>
            <p xml:id="p24">The reviews collected in this volume examine crowd-sourced editions from
                        various perspectives. Some projects place particular emphasis on the aspect
                        of <emph>citizen science</emph> and use participatory methods as a
                        tool for educational work and social engagement. Other projects focus more
                        strongly on the <emph>indexing of previously neglected source
                            materials</emph>, such as postcards, menus or other forms of everyday
                        documents. Still others can be understood as <emph>platform-based research infrastructures</emph> that primarily serve
                        specialised academic communities.</p>
            <p xml:id="p25">The contributions in this volume demonstrate that crowd editions now
                        constitute a diverse and dynamic field within digital scholarly editing. At
                        the same time, it becomes clear that many projects have so far been
                        inadequately documented or scientifically evaluated. Reviews can play an
                        important role here by making projects visible and comparable, situating
                        them within broader research contexts, and ensuring their long-term
                        documentation.</p>
            <p xml:id="p26">In the long term, the question arises as to what role participatory methods
                        will play in future editorial practice. Crowd editions are not only a tool
                        for managing large volumes of data, but also a testing ground for new forms
                        of collaboration between academia and the public. In a research landscape
                        increasingly characterised by openness, interdisciplinarity and digital
                        infrastructure, they could contribute to a greater understanding of
                        editorial work as a collective knowledge process.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="brumfield2017">Brumfield, Ben. 2017.
                        “Accidental Editors.” In <emph>Advances in Digital Scholarly
                            Editing: Papers Presented at the DiXiT Conferences in The Hague,
                            Cologne, and Antwerp</emph>, edited by Peter Boot, Anna Cappellotto and
                        Wout Dillen, 69–83. Leiden: Sidestone Press. <ref target="https://web.archive.org/web/20260410231134/https://www.sidestone.com/books/advances-in-digital-scholarly-editing">https://web.archive.org/web/20260410231134/https://www.sidestone.com/books/advances-in-digital-scholarly-editing</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="brumfield_evans2025">Brumfield, Ben,
                        and Connor Evans. 2025. What’s the Character Error Rate of a Volunteer?
                        Analyzing accuracy in cultural heritage crowdsourcing projects. Digital
                        Humanities Conference 2025, Lisbon, 18 July 2025. <ref target="http://zenodo.org/records/19494802">http://zenodo.org/records/19494802</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="busch_roeder2023">Busch, Anna, and
                        Torsten Roeder. 2023. „Crowdsourcing in digitalen Editionen – ein Themenband
                        der Rezensionszeitschrift RIDE.“ In <emph>Partizipative
                            Transkriptionsprojekte in Museen, Archiven und Bibliotheken</emph>, edited
                        by Diana Stört and Anita Hermannstädter, 47–49. Berlin: Museum für
                        Naturkunde Berlin (MfN) – Leibniz Institute for Evolution and Biodiversity
                        Science. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.7479/szm4-fs62">https://doi.org/10.7479/szm4-fs62</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="busch_etal2025">Busch, Anna, Torsten
                        Roeder, and Martin Prell. 2025. „‘Die Hölle, das sind die anderen.‘
                        Crowdsourcing in digitalen Editionen.“ DHd 2025: Under Construction
                        (DHd2025), Bielefeld, Germany. Zenodo,
                        2025. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14944585">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14944585</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="christoforou_etal2025">Christoforou,
                        Evgenia, Gianluca Demartini, and Jahna Otterbacher. 2025. “Crowdsourcing or
                        AI-Sourcing? Considering the impact of generative artificial intelligence on
                        data annotation tasks.” <emph>Communications of the ACM</emph>, 4
                        March
                        2025. <ref target="https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/crowdsourcing-or-ai-sourcing/">https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/crowdsourcing-or-ai-sourcing/</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="crompton_etal2013">Crompton,
                        Constance, Alyssa Arbuckle and Raymond Siemens. 2013. “Understanding the
                        Social Edition Through Iterative Implementation: The Case of the Devonshire
                        MS (BL Add MS 17492).” <emph>Scholarly and Research
                            Communication</emph>. 4
                   (3). <ref target="https://doi.org/10.22230/src.2013v4n3a118">https://doi.org/10.22230/src.2013v4n3a118</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="martin_etal2008">Martin, Nicole,
                        Stefan Lessmann, and Stefan Voß. 2008. „Crowdsourcing: Systematisierung
                        praktischer Ausprägungen und verwandter Konzepte.“ Multikonferenz
                        Wirtschaftsinformatik, MKWI 2008, Munich, 26 February 2008 – 28 February
                        2008, Proceedings.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ridge_2017">Ridge, Mia, ed. 2017.
                        Crowdsourcing Our Cultural Heritage. First issued in paperback. Digital
                        Research in the Arts and Humanities. London New York: Routledge, Taylor
                        &amp; Francis Group.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="ridge_etal2021">Ridge, Mia, Samantha
                        Blickhan, and Meghan Ferriter, eds. 2021 <emph>The Collective
                            Wisdom Handbook: Perspectives on Crowdsourcing in Cultural Heritage –
                            community review version</emph>.
                   PubPub. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.21428/a5d7554f.1b80974b">https://doi.org/10.21428/a5d7554f.1b80974b</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="smolarski_etal2023">Smolarski, René,
                        Hendrikje Carius, and Martin Prell, eds. 2023. “Citizen Science in den
                        Geschichtswissenschaften: methodische Perspektive oder perspektivlose
                        Methode?” <emph>DH &amp; CS - Schriften des Netzwerks für
                            digitale Geisteswissenschaften und Citizen Science</emph>, Vol. 3.
                        Göttingen: V&amp;R unipress.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="terras2015">Terras, Melissa. 2015.
                        “Crowdsourcing in the Digital Humanities”. In <emph>A New
                            Companion to Digital Humanities</emph>, edited by Susan Schreibman, Ray
                        Siemens and John Unsworth, 420–38. Chichester, UK: John Wiley &amp; Sons,
                        Ltd. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118680605.ch29">https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118680605.ch29</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="werner_cugliana2026">Werner, Nicolas,
                        and Elisa Cugliana. 2026. “Transcribing the Untranscribable: Automating
                        Recognition of Text and Image in Multimodal Medieval Manuscripts from Law to
                        Divination.” <emph>DHd 2026: Not Just Text, Not Just Data
                            (DHd2026)</emph>, Vienna, Austria.<ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.18696365">
                            Zenodo 2026
                                https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.18696365</ref>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
