<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/i-d-e/ride/master/schema/ride.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/i-d-e/ride/master/schema/ride.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ride.6.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>EDITORIAL: Reviewing Digital Text Collections</title>
                <author ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2852-065X">
                    <name>
                        <forename>Ulrike</forename>
                        <surname>Henny-Krahmer</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of Würzburg</orgName>
                        <placeName>Würzburg, Germany</placeName>
                    </affiliation>
                    <email>ulrike.henny (at) uni-wuerzburg.de</email>
                </author>
                <author ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298">
                    <name>
                        <forename>Frederike</forename>
                        <surname>Neuber</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of Cologne</orgName>
                        <placeName>Cologne, Germany</placeName>
                    </affiliation>
                    <email>neuber (at) i-d-e.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Institut für Dokumentologie und Editorik e.V.</publisher>
                <date when="2017-09">September 2017</date>
                <idno type="URI"
                    >http://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-6/editorial-reviewing-digital-text-collections/</idno>
                <idno type="DOI">10.18716/ride.a.6.0</idno>
                <idno type="archive"
                    >https://github.com/i-d-e/ride/raw/master/issues/issue06/editorial/editorial.pdf</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">RIDE - A review journal for digital editions and resources</title>
                <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2852-065X">Ulrike Henny-Krahmer</editor>
                <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298">Frederike Neuber</editor>
                <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6457-0913" role="managing">Philipp
                    Steinkrüger</editor>
                <editor ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/80243768" role="technical">Bernhard
                    Assmann</editor>
                <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2852-065X" role="technical">Ulrike
                    Henny-Krahmer</editor>
                <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298" role="technical">Frederike
                    Neuber</editor>
                <biblScope unit="issue" n="6">Digital Text Collections</biblScope>
                <idno type="URI">http://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-6</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>born digital</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>editorial</term>
                    <term>text collection</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="div1">
                <p xml:id="p1">We are pleased to present the sixth issue of the <emph>Review Journal
                        for Digital Editions and Resources</emph> (RIDE), published by the IDE since
                    2014, which is at the same time the first issue on Digital Text Collections
                    (DTC). We generally define DTCs as digital resources that involve the
                    collecting, structuring and enrichment of textual data and include in this
                    definition DTCs from various humanities disciplines such as Literary Studies,
                    Linguistics and History.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div2">
                <head>Motivation and scope</head>
                <p xml:id="p2">From the beginning, RIDE has been conceived not only as a reviewing
                    journal for digital scholarly editions but also for other kinds of resources
                    with relevance for Digital Humanities, including data sets of different types,
                    software and applications. The idea to edit an issue on DTC came up in late 2016
                    and was triggered by the following observations: While there is an ever growing
                    number of projects and studies in Digital Humanities creating and using large
                    sets of digital texts,<note xml:id="ftn1">To name individual projects in
                        concrete terms would lead too far. However, the fact that working with large
                        amounts of text has become a subject of various disciplines within the DH is
                        also shown by the increase in the number of relevant events as, for
                        instance, the seminar series “Corpus research in linguistics and beyond” at
                        the King’s College London (<ref
                            target="https://web.archive.org/web/20170909171938/https://www.kcl.ac.uk/sspp/departments/education/research/Research-Centres/ldc/seminars/corpus.aspx"
                            >https://web.archive.org/web/20170909171938/https://www.kcl.ac.uk/sspp/departments/education/research/Research-Centres/ldc/seminars/corpus.aspx</ref>),
                        the symposium “Text Mining in historical science” at the German Historical
                        Institute in Paris (<ref
                            target="https://web.archive.org/web/20170909172033/https://dhdhi.hypotheses.org/2714"
                            >https://web.archive.org/web/20170909172033/https://dhdhi.hypotheses.org/2714</ref>),
                        the Summer School at the University of Graz on “Computergestützte Analyse
                        und Verarbeitung von Sprache und Text - Text (and Data) Mining Methoden in
                        der geisteswissenschaftlichen Forschung” (<ref
                            target="https://web.archive.org/web/20170909172135/https://informationsmodellierung.uni-graz.at/de/veranstaltungen/summer-school-cast-2017/"
                            >https://web.archive.org/web/20170909172135/https://informationsmodellierung.uni-graz.at/de/veranstaltungen/summer-school-cast-2017/</ref>)
                        or the “Text Hackathon” at the Centre for Textual Studies at De Montfort
                        University (<ref
                            target="https://web.archive.org/web/20170909172252/http://cts.dmu.ac.uk/events/hackathon/"
                            >https://web.archive.org/web/20170909172252/http://cts.dmu.ac.uk/events/hackathon/</ref>).</note>
                    the methods and practices have not yet obtained the level of standardization and
                    best practice that has been reached in areas with a longer tradition in
                    corpus-based studies like Linguistics, for example. Often, research on or the
                    creation of new DTCs is based on already existing textual resources scattered
                    among the WWW. Therefore, it is crucial to establish common standards for the
                    documentation and provision of DTCs that support the exchange of textual data
                    while preventing a loss of quality and reliability. Finally, at present, the
                    various self-classifications of DTCs are ranging from “Corpus“ to “Digital
                    archive” to “Digital library” to “Repository” to many more; each of the terms,
                    however, can point to very different types of resources, containing very
                    different contents and applying very different methods. This lack of a common
                    nomenclature and classification impedes a further systematization of types of
                    DTCs and hinders the scholarly discourse about the resources. Such a discourse,
                    however, is desirable if DTCs are to play an ever more important role in
                    Humanities research.</p>
                <p xml:id="p3">We believe that reviewing DTCs systematically will (1) stimulate a
                    more vivid discourse about reliability and sustainability of textual data and
                    disseminate and canonize approved methods and approaches among disciplines; (2)
                    help to identify and compare various methodological frameworks, and thereby
                    provide an overview of the transfer of methods between single disciplines when
                    building DTCs in Digital Humanities; (3) contribute to sharpen terminologies and
                    concepts of different kinds of DTCs and in the long term lead to a more
                    differentiated understanding of what types of “text collections” exist and in
                    what way they differ from each other. Last but not least, we also want to raise
                    awareness of the scholarly work involved in designing and providing DTCs.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div3">
                <head>Methodological framework</head>
                <p xml:id="p4">To assure consistency and quality of the reviews on DTCs as much as
                    for the reviews on scholarly editions that have been published in RIDE so far,
                    we started to prepare the methodological and technical framework for <emph>RIDE
                        Digital Text Collections</emph> (RIDE-DTC) in late 2016. RIDE-DTC complies
                    with the standards that have been developed for academic journals. On
                    submission, reviews were blinded and referred to at least one external
                    peer-reviewer. Furthermore, in order to guide the reviewers when discussing the
                    projects, we developed a catalogue of criteria that covers a variety of relevant
                    aspects of DTCs: <emph>Criteria for Reviewing Digital Text Collections</emph>
                        (<ref target="https://www.i-d-e.de/criteria-text-collections-version-1-0"
                        >https://www.i-d-e.de/criteria-text-collections-version-1-0</ref>).<note
                        xml:id="ftn2">Ulrike Henny and Frederike Neuber, in collaboration with the
                        members of the IDE. <emph>Criteria for Reviewing Digital Text Collections,
                            version 1.0.</emph> February 2017. <ref
                            target="https://web.archive.org/web/20170909192316/http://www.i-d-e.de/criteria-text-collections-version-1-0"
                            >https://web.archive.org/web/20170909192316/http://www.i-d-e.de/criteria-text-collections-version-1-0</ref>.
                    </note> Besides addressing these aspects in their reviews, contributors were
                    asked to fill out a <emph>Questionnaire</emph> that accompanies the written text
                    as a factsheet (<ref
                        target="http://ride.i-d-e.de/questionnaire-text-collections/"
                        >http://ride.i-d-e.de/questionnaire-text-collections/</ref>). RIDE-DTC
                    encourages a global discourse on the topic. We invited reviews in English,
                    German, Italian, Spanish and French, all reviews, however, are accompanied by an
                    English abstract. While we first just planned a single special issue on DTCs for
                    which we published a dedicated call for reviews,<note xml:id="ftn3">
                        <ref
                            target="https://web.archive.org/web/20170909192450/http://ride.i-d-e.de/reviewers/call-for-reviews/special-issue-text-collections/"
                            >https://web.archive.org/web/20170909192450/http://ride.i-d-e.de/reviewers/call-for-reviews/special-issue-text-collections/</ref>.
                    </note> there were so many reactions that we decided to publish at least two
                    subsequent issues, this one being the first of them.</p>
                <p xml:id="p5">The reviews and questionnaires are encoded in XML/TEI and can be read
                    in an HTML version on the RIDE webpage or downloaded as PDF. Citability of
                    reviews is currently achieved through persistent URLs as well as DOIs. Finally,
                    we also visualize some of the data gathered from the questionnaires<note
                        xml:id="ftn4">
                        <ref target="http://ride.i-d-e.de/data/charts-text-collections"
                            >http://ride.i-d-e.de/data/charts-text-collections</ref>. </note> and
                    offer download-packages of all XML files and images via GitHub<note
                        xml:id="ftn5">
                        <ref target="https://github.com/i-d-e/ride/issue06"
                            >https://github.com/i-d-e/ride/issue06</ref>. </note> to facilitate
                    researchers with data for their own investigations and visualisations.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div4">
                <head>Content of the issue</head>
                <p xml:id="p6">
                    <figure xml:id="img1">
                        <graphic
                            url="http://ride.i-d-e.de/wp-content/uploads/issue_6/editorial/pictures/picture-1.png"/>
                        <head type="legend">Fields of research to which the projects have been
                            assigned by the reviewers.</head>
                    </figure> This issue includes ten reviews which display the heterogeneity of the
                    contents and scopes of DTCs out there. It features resources from Austria,
                    France, Germany, Ireland, Italy, Spain, Sweden, the United Kingdom and the
                    United States of America which have been reviewed in three different languages:
                    English (5), German (4) and Italian (1). The resources derive from various
                    disciplinary contexts. In the questionnaire provided by us, reviewers have so
                    far assigned the projects mainly to Literary studies, Linguistics and History
                    (see <ref type="crossref" target="#img1">Fig. 1</ref>).<note xml:id="ftn6"
                        >Multiple choices were possible.</note>
                </p>
                <p xml:id="p7">The ten reviews critically asses collections that consist of texts
                    derived from a specific type of textual carrier (e.g. books, manuscripts,
                    newspapers) and/or texts of a specific writing genre (e.g. sonnets, essays,
                    reviews) and/or texts that belong together because of a common historical,
                    cultural and/or linguistic background. The way in which the textual data is
                    modelled varies, too; from diplomatic to normalized transcriptions to summaries
                    of texts. Almost all of the text collections reviewed are presented via a
                    graphical user interface (GUI), usually a website, but there is also one review
                    focusing on a text collection with a GitHub repository as the primary access
                    point to the data. Obviously, the degree and kind of accessibility of the texts
                    influences the way in which the resources are discussed. Ideally, both the
                    underlying digital representation of the texts (e.g. TEI markup), as well as the
                    presentation of specific versions of the texts (e.g. prepared reading versions
                    on a website) can be considered in a review.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div5">
                <head>Classifying Digital Text Collections further</head>
                <p xml:id="p8">As we are particularly interested in the description of different
                    types of DTCs, we present the first results of our investigation into this topic
                    which was carried out during the preparation of this RIDE issue. Regarding the
                    classification of different types of text collections, we suggest a provisional
                    typology, which is part of the questionnaire that all the reviewers filled out.
                    While other approaches are possible, the definitions given here focus on
                    selection criteria, scope and aim of the text collection. Also, more specific
                    types of text collections do exist (such as a monitor corpus, for example) but
                    are not included in an attempt to give a list of the types of DTCs that we
                    consider “basic” from a Digital Humanities perspective:</p>
                <p>Basic types of DTCs: <list rend="bulleted">
                        <item>
                            <emph>General purpose collection</emph>: a text collection of a very
                            general nature (e.g. Wikisource, Project Gutenberg); often created in a
                            collaborative fashion; with no specific or very loose selection
                            criteria; usually not bound to a certain timeframe for its creation and
                            completion.</item>
                        <item>
                            <emph>Corpus</emph>: a collection of texts that has been created
                            according to some selection criteria (language, author, country, epoch,
                            genre, topic, style, etc.) which makes it more specific than a general
                            purpose collection; not necessarily aiming at completeness or
                            representativeness; e.g. the ‘Corpus of English Religious Prose’,
                            ‘Letters of 1916’, ‘Corpus of Literary Modernism’.</item>
                        <item>
                            <emph>Collection of records</emph>: a collection of texts that are held
                            together out of organisational reasons, e.g. a collection of historical
                            documents that has been kept in the same archive.</item>
                        <item>
                            <emph>Canon</emph>: collection of works that is considered most
                            important for a certain period, culture or discipline (e.g. the biblical
                            canon, the canon of English 19th century literature); might be formally
                            approved or authoritative and subject to debate and revision.</item>
                        <item>
                            <emph>Complete works/œuvre</emph> collection of all works by a single
                            author (e.g. complete works of Mark Twain).</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Common subtypes of <emph>Corpus</emph>: <list rend="bulleted">
                        <item>
                            <emph>Reference corpus</emph>: corpus that has been compiled in order to
                            be representative for a certain genre or language (e.g. reference corpus
                            of New High German Language). </item>
                        <item>
                            <emph>Contrastive corpus</emph>: corpus that aims at the systematic
                            comparison of its sub-components, to get to a description of differences
                            and similarities between them (e.g. FinDe, a contrastive corpus of
                            Finnish and German).</item>
                        <item>
                            <emph>Parallel corpus</emph>: corpus whose texts are contrasted with
                            other versions, often translations (e.g. the Parallel Bible Corpus). A
                            parallel corpus can be considered a certain kind of contrastive
                            corpus.</item>
                        <item>
                            <emph>Diachronic corpus</emph>: corpus that reflects the evolution (e.g.
                            of a language) over time (e.g. the Diachronic Corpus of Present-Day
                            Spoken English (c. 1960-1980)).</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p xml:id="p9">
                    <figure xml:id="img2">
                        <graphic
                            url="http://ride.i-d-e.de/wp-content/uploads/issue_6/editorial/pictures/picture-2.png"/>
                        <head type="legend">Comparison: self-classification of projects (l) and
                            classification of the DTCs by the reviewers (r).</head>
                    </figure> As to typological questions, reviewers were on the one hand asked for
                    the <emph>self-classification</emph> of the reviewed DTCs as given in their
                    titles and documentation. On the other hand, they were asked to classify the DTC
                    according to the <emph>typology</emph> above. For both questions
                    (self-classification and typology), it was possible to choose multiple options
                    as well as “other” in case none of the proposed options was perceived as
                    fitting. The following figure shows the results for these two questions (see
                        <ref type="crossref" target="#img2">Fig. 2</ref>) for the DTCs reviewed in
                    the current issue. Interestingly, eight out of ten of the text collections are
                    considered a “Corpus” by the reviewers, while only five designate themselves as
                    such. There are four self-branded “Collections” while only one of the text
                    collections is classified as a “General purpose collection” and two as
                    “Collection of records” by the reviewers. Three of the resources present
                    themselves as “Database” and thus place the focus of their self-definition on
                    aspects of the technical structure rather than on the methodological decisions
                    that define the composition and goals of the respective DTC. One resource
                    defines itself as a “Corpus” and “Digital Archive” at the same time. This raises
                    the question whether we are talking about two different lines of classification
                    here: one that concerns the composition of the DTC and the second that concerns
                    aspects of the institutional curation of the project.</p>
                <p xml:id="p10">These observations are helpful starting points when thinking about
                    how to systematize DTCs further, even if due to the small sample size it is too
                    early to draw any conclusions on this topic. However, it will be interesting to
                    see if the differences between self-classification of the projects and the
                    classification made by the reviewers (based on the typology we provided) persist
                    with future issues of RIDE-DTC. </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div6">
                <head>Reflections on the reviewing process in general</head>
                <p xml:id="p11">When working on this RIDE issue, we were confronted with some of the
                    general challenges that reviewing digital resources poses and which we would
                    like to comment on: the question of “reviewability” of a resource and the
                    possibility of productive response. Both are related to the potential
                    open-endedness of digital publications. One of the reviews discusses two states
                    of the resource’s graphical user-interface because the review was written in a
                    time when the GUI was about to change and two versions of it were accessible at
                    the same time. The historicity of a review could not be more palpable. In other
                    cases, reviewers had been in direct contact with the editors of the resource and
                    a discussion of future improvements of the text collection did already take
                    place during the writing process. This is laudable, but made it sometimes hard
                    to tell what is already there and what is going to be there as well as what is
                    public and what is only internal knowledge and documentation of the resource. A
                    third challenge are resources that are published in a distributed way and/or are
                    the result of a series of research projects. Where are the boundaries of the
                    resource that the review discusses?</p>
                <p xml:id="p12">All of these phenomena stress the importance of meticulously
                    delimiting the subject and documenting the sources of information when writing a
                    review. They also highlight the need for citability and versioning of the
                    resources under discussion. Certainly, these general issues about reviewing
                    digital resources need a more comprehensive as well as detailed discussion that
                    goes beyond this issue on DTCs and this editorial, in particular. By mentioning
                    them, we want to stress that they actually affect the day-to-day business of
                    reviewing. We hope that they will be picked up and discussed further by future
                    reviewers and those generally interested in the topic of evaluation and
                    reviewing of digital resources alike.</p>
                <p xml:id="p13">Finally, although we aim at maximum consistency regarding the
                    relevant aspects to discuss in a review of a DTC by providing a catalogue of
                    criteria and an accompanying questionnaire, at the end of the day the content
                    and tone of a review strongly depend on the author herself, her experiences with
                    the source, her taste and her writing style, with the review giving room for
                    individual judgement.</p>
                <p xml:id="p14">It was interesting and encouraging to see the many reactions to our
                    call for reviews for this RIDE issue. As a result, we welcome further
                    contributions for a second issue on DTCs which we plan to publish in the near
                        future.<note xml:id="ftn7">See the call for reviews: <ref
                            target="http://ride.i-d-e.de/reviewers/call-for-reviews/special-issue-text-collections/"
                            >http://ride.i-d-e.de/reviewers/call-for-reviews/special-issue-text-collections/</ref>.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Enjoy the RIDE!</p>
                <p>The editors, Ulrike Henny-Krahmer and Frederike Neuber, September 2017.</p>
            </div>
        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
