<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model https://raw.githubusercontent.com/i-d-e/ride/master/schema/ride.rng application/xml http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0?>
<?xml-model https://raw.githubusercontent.com/i-d-e/ride/master/schema/ride.rng application/xml http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ride.16.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>EDITORIAL: FAIR Enough? Evaluating Digital Scholarly Editions and the
                    Application of the FAIR Data Principles</title>
            <author ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8820-5112">
               <name>
                  <forename>Tessa</forename>
                  <surname>Gengnagel</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>University of Cologne</orgName>
                  <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/2886242">Cologne, Germany</placeName>
               </affiliation>
               <email>tessa.gengnagel@uni-koeln.de</email>
            </author>
            <author ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298">
               <name>
                  <forename>Frederike</forename>
                  <surname>Neuber</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</orgName>
                  <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/2950159">Berlin, Germany</placeName>
               </affiliation>
               <email>frederike.neuber@bbaw.de</email>
            </author>
            <author ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3167-5089">
               <name>
                  <forename>Daniela</forename>
                  <surname>Schulz</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>Herzog August Bibliothek Wolfenbüttel</orgName>
                  <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/2806914">Wolfenbüttel, Germany</placeName>
               </affiliation>
               <email>schulz@hab.de</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Institut für Dokumentologie und Editorik e.V.</publisher>
            <date when="2023-03">March 2023</date>
            <idno type="URI">http://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-16/editorial</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">10.18716/ride.a.16.0</idno>
            <idno type="archive">https://github.com/i-d-e/ride/raw/master/issues/issue16/editorial/editorial.pdf</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title level="j">RIDE - A review journal for digital editions and resources</title>
            <editor ref=" https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8820-5112">Tessa Gengnagel</editor>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298">Frederike Neuber</editor>
            <editor ref=" https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3167-5089">Daniela Schulz</editor>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2852-065X" role="managing">Ulrike
                    Henny-Krahmer</editor>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298" role="managing">Frederike
                    Neuber</editor>
            <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1438-3236" role="managing">Martina
                    Scholger</editor>
            <biblScope unit="issue" n="16">Digital Scholarly Editions</biblScope>
            <idno type="URI">http://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-16</idno>
            <idno type="DOI">10.18716/ride.a.16</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>editorial</term>
               <term>digital scholarly editions</term>
               <term>fair</term>
               <term>Text+</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="div1">
            <p xml:id="p1">Digital scholarly editions have revolutionized the global
                    accessibility of scholarly editions – but what are the standards that they
                    adhere to (or should adhere to) in order to meet basic requirements of long-term
                    availability? How are digital editions currently available, what parts of them
                    are available for what purpose? And are they merely accessible or are they
                    discoverable as well? These are some of the questions that the field of digital
                    scholarly editing still needs to address.<note xml:id="ftn1">Such questions will
                        often feature implicitly but are rarely the focus of debate. Previous
                        scholarship on this topic (in particular under the impression of the FAIR
                        principles) include an article on the sustainability in multi-year research
                        projects based on the example of hallerNet, which is a research and edition
                        platform focused on the cross-linking of different collections from the
                        period between 1700 and 1850 (<ref type="crossref" target="#daengelistuber2020">Dängeli/Stuber 2020</ref>), and an
                        unpublished master thesis by Jürgen Windeck titled “FAIRe digitale
                        Editionen. Anforderungen für nutzbare wissenschaftliche Editionen” (<ref type="crossref" target="#windeck2019">Windeck 2019</ref>). Beyond that,
                        a comprehensive discussion remains a desideratum.</note> With this RIDE
                    issue, we present an important contribution by evaluating editions with special
                    attention paid to the way they comply with the FAIR data principles, which serve
                    as a guideline for ensuring the sustainability and re-usability of data.<note xml:id="ftn2">See <ref target="https://web.archive.org/web/20230209115851/https://www.go-fair.org/fair-principles/">https://web.archive.org/web/20230209115851/https://www.go-fair.org/fair-principles/</ref>.</note>
                    These principles have gained acceptance in various research communities since
                    they were first proposed in 2016 (<ref type="crossref" target="#wilkinson2016">Wilkinson et al. 2016</ref>). According to FAIR, data needs to be
                    <emph>Findable</emph>, <emph>Accessible</emph>, <emph>Interoperable</emph>
                    and <emph>Reusable</emph> both for human scholars and machines. Since the
                    principles are formulated in broad and general terms, their specific application
                    and implementation needs to be assessed and adapted depending on the
                    disciplinary context.</p>
            <p xml:id="p2">The framework in this case is provided not only by the field of
                    digital scholarly editing but also by efforts within Germany to standardize and
                    stabilize research data infrastructures. For this reason, the German National
                    Research Data Infrastructure (NFDI) was initiated between 2016–2018.<note xml:id="ftn3">With its recommendation in 2016, the German Council for
                        Scientific Information Infrastructures provided the impetus for the
                        establishment of a National Research Data Infrastructure (NFDI). This
                        recommendation was approved by the Joint Science Conference in 2018. One of
                        the goals of the NFDI is the systematic provision of research data in
                        accordance with the FAIR Data Principles.</note> Since 2021, the NFDI Text+ consortium is dedicated to the domain of text- and language-based data,
                    particularly collections, lexical resources, and scholarly editions. A central
                    aim of the task area ‘editions’ is the development of recommendations for the
                    creation, processing, and publication of FAIR research data. The implementation
                    of the FAIR principles is crucial for central aspects of working with digital
                    editions; these include, for example, aspects of search, linking, licensing, and
                    re-use. In order to gain a better understanding of what “FAIR” entails in the
                    context of editions specifically and whether and how these principles can be
                    applied to digital scholarly editions, existing practices are best described in
                    the form of reviews. On the basis of individual case studies, reviews allow a
                    survey of the diverse editorial landscape and can thus contribute to the
                    development of new criteria. For this reason, Text+ has chosen to cooperate with
                    the review journal RIDE. Together, Text+ and RIDE seek to further promote the
                    discourse on best practices in the creation and publication of digital editions
                    in general and in the application of the FAIR principles in particular.</p>
            <p xml:id="p3">In order to provide reviewers with a guideline to assist them in
                    their reviewing, criteria for evaluating the FAIRness of editions (<ref type="crossref" target="#gengnageletal2022">Gengnagel, Neuber and Schulz
                        2022</ref>) have been developed in the context of Text+ to supplement the
                    IDE’s general set of reviewing criteria (<ref type="crossref" target="#sahle2014">Sahle 2014</ref>). The current issue is the first to be
                    published from the responses to the Call for Reviews published in April
                        2022.<note xml:id="ftn4">See <ref target="https://web.archive.org/web/20230227084840/https://ride.i-d-e.de/reviewers/call-for-reviews/ride-textplus-en/">https://web.archive.org/web/20230227084840/https://ride.i-d-e.de/reviewers/call-for-reviews/ride-textplus-en/</ref>
               </note>
                    It contains five reviews of the following digital editions: <list rend="bulleted">
                  <item>“Walter Benjamin digital”, a digital edition that partly complements
                            an already printed edition of the author’s works and becomes a reading
                            aid and research tool for users through the close interlinking of images
                            and text of Benjamin’s drafts; </item>
                  <item>“Digitale Edition und Kommentierung der Tagebücher des Fürsten
                            Christian II. von Anhalt-Bernburg (1599–1656)”, which aims at presenting
                            the complete diaries of the prince from Early Modern times; </item>
                  <item>“Briefportal Leibniz. Ausgewählte Briefe in HTML”, a digital
                            collection of selected letters of the ongoing critical print edition of
                            the German polymath Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz’ works and letters which
                            attempts to overcome some limitations of the printed volumes; </item>
                  <item>“Theodor Fontane’s Notebooks: A ‘Digital Genetic-Critical and
                            Commented Edition’”, which presents the notebooks of the 19th-century
                            German writer in a born-digital edition with a strong focus on the
                            materiality of the documents; </item>
                  <item>“Die Urkunden und Akten des Klosters und des Oberamts Königsfelden
                            1308–1662”, which provides access to more than 1500 charters with a
                            focus on their contents for research on the history of Switzerland.
                        </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="p4">The editions reviewed have some similarities and differences, some of
                    which may affect their outcome and influence the implementation of FAIR
                    principles. Generally, the editions originate from various disciplines,
                    including literary studies, philosophy, history or regional history, and history
                    of science. This represents the broad spectrum of disciplines and research areas
                    that is also covered in Text+ with regard to text and language data. Moreover,
                    the reviewed resources represent the variety of sources (drafts, notebooks,
                    charters, letters, diaries) and the different models and traditions to capture,
                    enrich, and present them (e. g. genetic edition, historical-critical edition,
                    diplomatic edition) which characterize the field of scholarly editing.</p>
            <p xml:id="p5">Among the five reviewed editions, two editions - “Briefportal
                    Leibniz” and “Walter Benjamin Digital” - are not primarily digital editions (i.
                    e. born-digital) but rather supplements to printed editions. Accordingly, these
                    editions are likely to have fewer resources available which affects the
                    selection of documents and the text presentation on the one hand and the
                    complexity of technical implementation and application of FAIR principles on the
                    other. Furthermore, the maturity of the edition also plays a role in the
                    implementation of FAIR principles. For instance, the edition of the diaries of
                    Fürst Christian II. is still work-in-progress and the Königsfelden edition is a
                    relatively young resource, thus for both editions adjustments to the FAIR
                    compliance can still be expected. The benefits of making research data available
                    are particularly evident in the review on the Fontane edition, which, in addition to an
                    evaluation by means of a discursive text, also carries out a machine evaluation
                    of the encoding. At the same time, however, the resource and its strict
                    licensing also show that accessible data does not necessarily guarantee
                    reusability.</p>
            <p xml:id="p6">In summary, after examining the first five reviews in terms of
                    developing recommendations for applying FAIR principles in digital editions in
                    the context of Text+, we can conclude: First, digital editions are living objects, often
                    published work-in-progress, which must be taken into account when implementing
                    and assessing the FAIR principles, for example when there are different versions
                    of an edition. Second, depending on the project context and available resources
                    (manpower, time, financing, technical know-how), the application of the FAIR
                    principles may vary, which in turn means that recommendations on how to
                    implement the principles should be scalable accordingly. Third, policies and
                    modes of data provision such as the FAIR Principles, Open Access, and Creative
                    Commons are often used and interpreted synonymously but need to be clearly
                    differentiated and related to each other.</p>
            <p xml:id="p7">We were very pleased with the response to the Call for Reviews and
                    can already announce that there will be a second issue in the near future. The
                    five reviews show once again how diverse the editing landscape is and thus also
                    the implementation of the FAIR principles.</p>
            <p>Enjoy the RIDE!</p>
            <p>The editors, Tessa Gengnagel, Frederike Neuber, and Daniela Schulz, March
                    2023.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="daengelistuber">Dängeli, Peter and Martin Stuber. 2020.
                        “Nachhaltigkeit in langjährigen Erschliessungsprojekten: FAIR-Data-Kriterien
                        bei Editions- und Forschungsplattformen zum 18. Jahrhundert”,
                            <emph>xviii.ch: Jahrbuch der Schweizerischen Gesellschaft zur
                            Erforschung des 18. Jahrhunderts 11</emph>, p. 34–51. DOI: <ref target="https://boris.unibe.ch/151721/2/10_24894_2673-4419_00004_8138.pdf">10.24894/2673-4419.00004</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="gengnageletal2022">Gengnagel, Tessa, Neuber, Frederike, and
                        Daniela Schulz. 2022. “Criteria for Reviewing the Application of FAIR
                        Principles in Digital Scholarly Editions, Version 1.1.” <emph>RIDE: <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/">A Review Journal for Digital
                                Editions and Resources</ref>.</emph>
                  <ref target="https://web.archive.org/web/20230120155729/https:/ride.i-d-e.de/fair-criteria-editions/">https://web.archive.org/web/20230120155729/https://ride.i-d-e.de/fair-criteria-editions/</ref>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="sahle2014">Sahle, Patrick (with contributions by Georg Vogeler et
                        al.). 2014. Kriterien für die Besprechung digitaler Editionen, Version
                        1.1.” <emph>RIDE: A Review Journal for Digital Editions and Resources
                        </emph>
                  <ref target="https://web.archive.org/web/20230120160031/https:/www.i-d-e.de/publikationen/weitereschriften/kriterien-version-1-1/">https://web.archive.org/web/20230120160031/https://www.i-d-e.de/publikationen/weitereschriften/kriterien-version-1-1/</ref>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="wilkinson2016">Wilkinson, M. D. et al. 2016. “The FAIR Guiding
                        Principles for scientific data management and stewardship”. <emph>Scientific
                            Data,</emph> 3: 1–9. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18">https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2016.18</ref>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="windeck2019">Windeck, Jürgen. 2019. <emph>FAIRe digitale Editionen.
                        Anforderungen für nutzbare wissenschaftliche Editionen</emph>. Master thesis, TH
                        Köln.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
