<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/i-d-e/ride/master/schema/ride.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/i-d-e/ride/master/schema/ride.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ride.8.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>EDITORIAL: Digital Text Collections, Take two - Action!</title>
                <author ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298">
                    <name>
                        <forename>Frederike</forename>
                        <surname>Neuber</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
                        <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                    </affiliation>
                    <email>neuber@bbaw.de</email>
                </author>
                <author ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2852-065X">
                    <name>
                        <forename>Ulrike</forename>
                        <surname>Henny-Krahmer</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of Würzburg</orgName>
                        <placeName>Würzburg</placeName>
                    </affiliation>
                    <email>ulrike.henny@uni-wuerzburg.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Institut für Dokumentologie und Editorik e. V.</publisher>
                <date when="2018-02">February 2018</date>
                <idno type="URI">http://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-8/editorial</idno>
                <idno type="DOI">10.18716/ride.a.8.0</idno>
                <idno type="archive"
                    >https://github.com/i-d-e/ride/raw/master/issues/issue08/editorial/editorial.pdf</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="j">RIDE - A review journal for digital editions and resources</title>
                <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2852-065X">Ulrike Henny-Krahmer</editor>
                <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298">Frederike Neuber</editor>
                <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6457-0913" role="managing">Philipp
                    Steinkrüger</editor>
                <editor ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/80243768" role="technical">Bernhard
                    Assmann</editor>
                <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2852-065X" role="technical">Ulrike
                    Henny-Krahmer</editor>
                <editor ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8279-9298" role="technical">Frederike
                    Neuber</editor>
                <biblScope unit="issue" n="8">Digital Text Collections</biblScope>
                <idno type="URI">http://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-8</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>born digital</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>editorial</term>
                    <term>text collection</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="div1">
                <p xml:id="p1">Welcome to the second issue of RIDE <emph>Digital Text
                        Collections</emph> (DTC), which is published as Issue 8 in the RIDE series.
                    We have been working on this issue since last summer. After the initial major
                    interest in reviewing DTCs which lead to the publication of ten reviews in the
                    first issue, we now return to the usual rhythm of publication for RIDE issues,
                    presenting five new reviews.</p>
                <p xml:id="p2">As always, this issue is based on the methodological framework of
                    RIDE. Firstly, the reviewers were asked to consider the key aspects of the
                    catalogue of <emph>
                        <ref target="https://www.i-d-e.de/criteria-text-collections-version-1-0"
                            >Criteria for Reviewing Digital Text Collections</ref>
                    </emph> when discussing the respective resource. Secondly, each contribution is
                    subjected to a peer reviewing process and finally, each review is supplemented
                    by a factsheet resulting from a <ref
                        target="http://ride.i-d-e.de/questionnaire-text-collections/"
                        >questionnaire</ref>. Some statistics resulting from the questionnaires of
                    all reviews on digital text collections so far can be consulted <ref
                        target="http://ride.i-d-e.de/data/charts-text-collections">here</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div2">
                <head>Contents</head>
                <p xml:id="p3">The current issue contains four reviews in English and one in German,
                    which are devoted to DTCs originating from different contexts. Two of the
                    reviews discuss textual resources which are of great importance for the study of
                    Classical Antiquity: <emph>Perseus Digital Library</emph>, reviewed by Sarah
                    Lang, and <emph>PHI Latin Texts</emph>, by Dániel Kozák. Another two reviews in
                    this issue are devoted to DTCs which are characterised above all by their
                    dedication to a specific literary genre: <emph>Anemoskala</emph>, a collection
                    of texts of and a concordance tool for Modern Greek poetry, reviewed by
                    Anna-Maria Sichani, and <emph>Théâtre Classique</emph>, a collection of
                    French-language dramas from the Classical Age and Enlightenment, reviewed by
                    Christof Schöch. Finally, this issue also contains a review that does not
                    primarily originate from the scholarly context, although it is widely used in
                    it: <emph>Wikisource</emph>, precisely: the Wikisource subcollection of texts in
                    German language, reviewed by Susanne Haaf. What is special about this collection
                    when compared to the other resources reviewed in this issue is that it does not
                    have a clearly defined scholarly editorial team behind it, but rather a group of
                    volunteers, often laymen.</p>
                <p xml:id="p4">
                    <figure xml:id="img1">
                        <graphic
                            url="http://ride.i-d-e.de/wp-content/uploads/issue_8/editorial/pictures/picture-1.png"/>
                        <head type="legend">Comparison: self-classification of projects (left) and
                            classification of the DTCs by the reviewers (right).</head>
                    </figure> In the editorial of the last issue, we focused mainly on questions of
                    the classification of DTCs from a terminological point of view, providing a
                    working terminology to further systematize types of DTCs (see the <ref
                        target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issues/issue-6/editorial-reviewing-digital-text-collections/"
                        >previous editorial</ref>). It became clear, however, that the
                    self-designation of resources does not necessarily have to correspond to the
                    type chosen by the reviewers.</p>
                <p xml:id="p5">
                    <ref type="crossref" target="#img1">Fig. 1</ref> shows an updated version of the
                    comparison between the self-classification of the projects as given in their
                    titles and documentation on the one hand, and the classification of the DTCs by
                    the reviewers, on the other hand.<note xml:id="ftn1">As before, multiple options
                        could be chosen, as well as “other” in cases where none of the proposed
                        options was considered adequate.</note> The charts include all the data
                    gathered for DTCs in the 15 reviews so far. As before, the concept of
                        <emph>corpus</emph> is used more often by the reviewers than in the
                    self-designation of the resources (11 times vs. 6).<note xml:id="ftn2">According
                        to the last issue, the definition of <emph>corpus</emph> is: “a collection
                        of texts that has been created according to some selection criteria
                        (language, author, country, epoch, genre, topic, style, etc.) which makes it
                        more specific than a general-purpose collection; not necessarily aiming at
                        completeness or representativeness; e.g. the ‘Corpus of English Religious
                        Prose’, ‘Letters of 1916’, ‘Corpus of Literary Modernism’”.</note> It has to
                    be emphasized here that the taxonomy proposed by us focuses on aspects of the
                    selection of materials and design of the DTCs in terms of content and research
                    aims (e.g. to provide a loosely structured <emph>general-purpose text
                        collection</emph> vs. a <emph>parallel corpus</emph> aiming at the
                    comparison of specific groups of texts). The self-designation, on the other
                    hand, also tends to refer to the aspects of storage, organisation, and
                    presentation of the materials (digital archive, digital library, portal,
                    database).</p>
                <p xml:id="p6">There is still a long way to go before sharp definitions of what
                    constitutes which kind of text collection can be provided. However, the primary
                    objective of our proposal is not to set terminological boundaries. Instead, we
                    would like to raise awareness for terminological questions and promote a
                    discourse that sets out the whole range of possible types of DTCs, based on the
                    observations gained from the reviews. In the following, three aspects are
                    discussed that came up during the editing of this issue and which we consider to
                    be particularly important for the consideration and evaluation of DTCs.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div3">
                <head>On scholarliness</head>
                <p xml:id="p7">When considering different types of DTCs, the issue of scholarliness
                    becomes relevant, too. While the <ref
                        target="https://www.i-d-e.de/publikationen/weitereschriften/criteria-version-1-1/"
                        >Criteria for Reviewing Scholarly Digital Editions</ref> include the
                    difference between scholarly and non-scholarly editions as a component in the
                    very definition of the digital edition, we consciously avoided a clear
                    distinction of scholarly and non-scholarly text collections in the <ref
                        target="https://www.i-d-e.de/publikationen/weitereschriften/criteria-text-collections-version-1-0/"
                        >Criteria for Reviewing Digital Text Collections</ref>. We did so because
                    there are many general-purpose text collections out there which have not been
                        <emph>created</emph> in an academic context aiming to meet scholarly
                    standards, but which are nonetheless <emph>used</emph> in scholarly
                    undertakings. This is true, for example, for the <emph>Wikisource</emph>
                    collection reviewed in this issue. Again, in the case of <emph>Théâtre
                        Classique</emph>, the question is to what extent the collected texts can be
                    considered scholarly texts. Once reviewed, general-purpose collections and
                    especially larger DTCs see themselves exposed to questions of textual quality
                    and the reviewers are challenged to discuss their understanding of scholarly
                    standards.</p>
                <p xml:id="p8">In her review, Haaf cites a statement reflecting the self-conception
                    of <emph>Wikisource</emph>: “<emph>Wikisource</emph> versteht sich als
                    wissenschaftlich fundiertes Qualitätsprojekt, das sich möglichst hohen Standards
                    bei der Textwiedergabe verpflichtet sieht.”<note xml:id="ftn3"
                            >“<emph>Wikisource</emph> sees itself as a scholarly grounded project
                        which is bound to high standards of text reproduction as much as possible”
                        (translated by the editors), see Haaf, Susanne. 2018. "Rezension der
                        Deutschsprachigen Wikisource." <emph>RIDE</emph> 8, § 2. doi:
                        10.18716/ride.a.8.4 <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-8/wikisource/"
                            >https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-8/wikisource/</ref>, accessed: February
                            23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi>, 2018.</note> In the discussion, she then
                    focuses particularly on the limits of <emph>Wikisource</emph>’s claim to
                    scholarliness, but also stresses the value of the resource for scholarly
                    purposes. In a similar vein, Schöch observes about <emph>Théâtre
                        Classique</emph>: “It is unclear whether any formal quality assurance of the
                    transcriptions, annotations, and metadata has been or is being performed” and
                    later on concludes “this is certainly no scholarly text edition, but could
                    rather be described as a text collection for scholarly use”.<note xml:id="ftn4"
                        >Schöch, Christof. 2018. "Review of 'Théâtre Classique'." <emph>RIDE</emph>
                        8, § 11. doi: 10.18716/ride.a.8.5 <ref
                            target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-8/theatre-classique/"
                            >https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-8/theatre-classique/</ref>, accessed:
                        February 23, 2018.</note>
                </p>
                <p xml:id="p9">It becomes clear that various factors influence the perception and
                    evaluation of the scholarliness of a DTC: the institutional, organizational, and
                    personal background, transparency in terms of text establishment (Where do the
                    texts come from? According to which criteria have they been selected? How have
                    they been treated?), the presence or absence of reports of quality control, but
                    also factors such as the size of a DTC. While there are already well-known
                    standards for text treatment in digital scholarly editions (DSE), no such
                    standards have yet been established for large DTCs which are, amongst other
                    things, used for quantitative text analysis and which necessarily have to draw
                    on a different set of quality criteria than a focused scholarly edition. It is
                    thus not coincidental that both mentioned reviews refer to the DSE when
                    discussing the scholarliness of a DTC. There is obviously a need for more
                    discussion of aspects of quality assurance and scholarly standards for DTCs.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div4">
                <head>On access and provision</head>
                <p xml:id="p10">Another aspect of DTCs that we regard as in need of discussion is
                    the disproportion of online accessible DTCs and the lack of possibilities to
                    harvest the data from these resources. The accessibility and provision of the
                    data is discussed in some of our reviews and can be also observed in our
                    statistics. <ref type="crossref" target="#img2">Fig. 2</ref> shows the results
                    of the questionnaire for the following four questions related to access to the
                    texts: <list rend="bulleted">
                        <item>Under what license are the contents released?</item>
                        <item>Is the textual data accessible in a source format (e.g.
                            XML,TXT)?</item>
                        <item>Are there technical interfaces which allow the reuse of the data of
                            the text collection in other contexts?</item>
                        <item>Can the entire raw data of the project be downloaded (as a
                            whole)?</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p xml:id="p11">
                    <figure xml:id="img2">
                        <graphic
                            url="http://ride.i-d-e.de/wp-content/uploads/issue_8/editorial/pictures/picture-2.png"/>
                        <head type="legend">Licenses (top left), technical interfaces for reuse (top
                            right), access to textual data (bottom left), and download options for
                            raw data (bottom right) for DTCs.</head>
                    </figure> There is a general tendency towards an “open policy” for providing
                    textual resources via a user web interface and to allow reuse of the texts in
                    principle by setting appropriate licenses. For almost two-thirds of the
                    projects, the reviewers indicated licenses that allow further reuse. However,
                    this trend to “openness” is not reflected to the same extent in the availability
                    of overall download options and technical interfaces which would facilitate the
                    reuse of the texts on a large scale. According to our statistics, only slightly
                    more than half of the DTCs provide their textual resources in a reusable source
                    format (7 out of 15), and even less DTCs (one third) offer their data for
                    downloading. For almost half of the reviewed DTCs, the reviewers indicated the
                    existence of an API.<note xml:id="ftn5">At this point, our data set is still too
                        small to allow an extrapolation of this disproportion to DTCs in general.
                        However, we will continue to observe the development of the statistics
                        regarding licensing and provision of data in the future.</note>
                </p>
                <p xml:id="p12">Our statistics do not show a drastic picture in this sense, as many
                    creators of DTCs seem to be aware that the data can be used in other contexts
                    and decide to offer them accordingly. On the other hand, however, it is
                    disappointing that many projects still seem not to prioritize the free
                    availability of their data, leaving many high-quality textual data "locked up"
                    in the respective resource. Sichani describes this contradictory situation of
                    access to the contents as “‘read-only’ or ‘see-but-not-touch’ mode”.<note
                        xml:id="ftn6">Sichani, Anna-Maria. 2018. "Anemoskala: corpus and
                        concordances for major Modern Greek poets.” <emph>RIDE</emph> 8, §26 and §27
                        in the following. doi: 10.18716/ride.a.8.1 <ref
                            target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-8/anemoskala/"
                            >https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-8/anemoskala/</ref>, accessed: February 23,
                        2018.</note> In her review on <emph>Anemoskala</emph> she suggests that
                    “text collections should not be seen as the end-product or an end in itself but
                    as the starting point for sophisticated computational processing activities” and
                    pleads to give access to the source data in order to “move beyond ‘screen
                    essentialism’”.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div5">
                <head>On long-standing projects</head>
                <p xml:id="p13">The last aspect we want to discuss is the challenge of reviewing
                    DTCs with a long history, such as <emph>PHI Latin Texts</emph> or <emph>Perseus
                        Digital Library</emph>. Both are, so to speak, “dinosaurs” of DTCs.
                        <emph>Perseus</emph> has been developed online since the 1980s and is still
                    being developed further, in close connection with other classical resources in
                    the WWW. <emph>PHI Latin Texts</emph> appeared on CD-ROM since the early 1990s
                    and is online available since 2011. It is apparently no longer being
                    continued.</p>
                <p xml:id="p14">In general, there is more heterogeneity and inconsistency to be
                    expected from long-standing DTCs. The state of the texts included may be
                    non-uniform when they have been prepared in different phases. Indeed, Lang
                    declares in her review, that “every generation of <emph>Perseus</emph> texts
                    followed a different paradigm of production”.<note xml:id="ftn7">Lang, Sarah.
                        2018. "Review of ‘Perseus Digital Library’” <emph>RIDE</emph> 8, § 4 in the
                        following. doi: 10.18716/ride.a.8.3 <ref
                            target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-8/Perseus"
                            >https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-8/Perseus</ref>, accessed: February 23,
                        2018.</note> It is likewise possible that the methods used stem from an
                    earlier period and do not necessarily reflect the state of the art in creating
                    DTCs. A review needs to take into account the historicity of the resource and
                    the context in which it has emerged. For instance, Kozák notes in his review on
                        <emph>PHI Latin Texts</emph>, that the DTC “is not based on up-to-date
                    standards for the digital encoding, access, and presentation of textual data”.
                    However, he emphasises at the same time that it “has proven to be in practice a
                    wonderful tool [...], widely used by classical philologists for decades
                        now”.<note xml:id="ftn8">Kozák, Dániel. 2018. "Review of ‘PHI Latin Texts’”
                            <emph>RIDE</emph> 8, § 17 in the following. doi: 10.18716/ride.a.8.2
                            <ref target="https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-8/phi"
                            >https://ride.i-d-e.de/issue-8/phi</ref>, accessed: February 23,
                        2018.</note> Finally, also the relation of the reviewed DTC to other
                    resources must be considered. Side projects may have emerged from historical
                    core projects, or they may have been absorbed in a bigger project.</p>
                <p xml:id="p15">The above-mentioned aspects of long-standing projects require a
                    particularly differentiated consideration and some aspects can only be examined
                    briefly within a single review (e.g. the relation to other resources). However,
                    it should be emphasised that long-standing DTCs are at the same time of
                    particular interest for reviewing, precisely <emph>because of</emph> their
                    history. In a way they document the development the Digital Humanities have
                    undergone in the last decades. Lang attests <emph>Perseus</emph> in her synopsis
                    a value that goes beyond the actual contents of the DTC: “The project has had a
                    great methodological impact on the discussion of best practises for the Digital
                    Humanities and has been a pioneer of the field.”<note xml:id="ftn9">Lang § 32,
                        see <ref type="crossref" target="#ftn7">ftn. 7</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p xml:id="p16">The publication of this issue, like the previous one, has once again
                    demonstrated how diverse textual resources in the World Wide Web are, be it with
                    regard to their creation, scholarly enrichment, provision, or distribution. The
                    particularities of the resources hold challenges when discussing them.<note
                        xml:id="ftn10">At the annual conference of “Digital Humanities in the German
                        speaking countries” (<ref target="http://dhd2018.uni-koeln.de/"
                            >DHd2018</ref>) we will discuss some of the difficulties when reviewing
                        digital resources such as text collections and scholarly editions in a
                        dedicated panel: “Alles ist im Fluss. Ressourcen und Rezensionen in den
                        Digital Humanities”, Wednesday, February 28, 2018 (submitted by F. Neuber,
                        U. Henny-Krahmer, P. Sahle and F. Fischer).</note> Together with us, the
                    reviewers of this issue have embraced the challenges of reviewing DTCs with
                    great enthusiasm. We want to thank everyone involved in the creation of this
                    issue and hope you enjoy reading it.</p>
                <p>The editors, Frederike Neuber and Ulrike Henny-Krahmer, February 2018.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>